<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> -->
<!-- This third-party XSLT can be enabled for direct transformations in XML processors, including most browsers -->


<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- If further character entities are required then they should be added to the DOCTYPE above.
     Use of an external entity file is not recommended. -->

<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="info"
  docName="draft-link-v6ops-claton-01"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates="8585"
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">
  <front>
<title abbrev="claton">464 Customer-side Translator (CLAT): Node Recommendations</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-link-v6ops-claton"/>
    <author fullname="Jen Linkova" initials="J" surname="Linkova">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->
          <street>1 Darling Island Rd</street>
          <city>Pyrmont</city>
          <region>NSW</region>
          <code>2009</code>
          <country>AU</country>
        </postal>        
        <email>furry13@gmail.com</email>  
        <email>furry@google.com</email>  
      </address>
    </author>
<author initials="T." surname="Jensen" fullname="Tommy Jensen">
      <organization showOnFrontPage="true">Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>tojens@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2023"/>
<area>Ops</area>
    <workgroup>IPv6 operations</workgroup>
    <keyword>ipv6</keyword>
    <keyword>slaac</keyword>
    <keyword>464xlat</keyword>
    <keyword>clat</keyword>
    <keyword>nat64</keyword>
    <keyword>pref64</keyword>
    <keyword>ipv6-only</keyword>
    <keyword>ipv6-mostly</keyword>


    <abstract>
 <t>
464XLAT (<xref target="RFC6877"/>) defines an arcitecture for providing IPv4 connectivity across an IPv6-only network.
The solution  contains two key elements: provider-side translator (PLAT) and customer-side translator (CLAT).
This document provides recommendations on when a node shall enable or disable CLAT.
</t>

    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
      <name>Introduction</name>
<t>
464XLAT is widely deployed in 3GPP networks (as described in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC6877"/>) where a mobile phone performs the CLAT function, providing a private IPv4 address and IPv4 default route for the applications and tethered devices.
Enabling 464XLAT allowed mobile operators to migrate User Equipment (UE) devices (also known as mobile phones) to IPv6-only mode, where those devices are only assigned IPv6 addresses.
</t>
<t>
Until recently, IPv6-only hosts were rather uncommon outside of mobile networks and datacenters.
Even if the network provide PLAT in the form of NAT64, hosts like desktops and laptops still need the network to provide IPv4 addresses, as otherwise IPv4-only applications fail.
However as more and more operating systems outside of 3GPP world support CLAT, it becomes possible to migrate those devices to IPv6-only mode.
So networks like public WiFi, enterprise networks or even home networks can deploy 464XLAN as described in Section 4.2 of <xref target="RFC6877"/>:
</t>
<ul>
<li>
<t>PLAT functions are performed by NAT64 network devices.</t>
</li>
<li>
<t>
CLAT is performed by the host itself.
</t>
</li>
</ul>

<t>
Another 464XLAT deployment model is a Wireline one (section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC6877"/>), when a CPE router is connected to an IPv6-only network and provides CLAT functions for IPv4-enabled downstream devices. <xref target="RFC8585"/> specifies 464XLAT support requirements for such devices.
</t>

<t>
For both scenarios to work, the node performing CLAT (such as a host or a CPE router) need to enable the CLAT when connecting to an IPv6-only network.
This document complement <xref target="RFC6877"/> by  providing recommendations for the node developers on enabling and disabling CLAT functions.
</t>

    </section>
      
      <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
          "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
          RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
          interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
          <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
          all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>

<section anchor="term">
<name>
Terminology
</name>
<t>
To be added
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="multihomed">
<name>Multiple Interfaces Considerations</name>
<t>
A node may have multiple IPv6-only interfaces (for example, a mobile phone can be connected to an IPv6-only WiFi network and to an IPv6-only mobile network).
In that case the mode SHOULD run an independent dedicated CLAT instance on each interface connected to a network equipped with PLAT.
Consequently, each CLAT instance SHOULD install a separate default IPv4 route on each CLAT-enabled interface.
The metrics of IPv4 routes SHOULD be consistent with the metrics of IPv6 default routes.
</t>
</section>

    <section anchor="enable">
<name>Enabling CLAT</name>
<t>
To enable CLAT, the node needs discover the PLAT-side translation IPv6 prefix, also known as NAT64 prefix (see Section 6.3 of <xref target="RFC6877"/>).
PREF64 Router Advertisement option (<xref target="RFC8781"/>) provides that information and can be used as a strong indication that the network supports NAT64 (PLAT) function.
Therefore the node SHOULD enable CLAT if it receives an Router Advertisement containing PREF64 option.
</t>
<t>
If RAs received by the node do not contain PREF64 option, the node MAY use other mechanisms to detect the PLAT presence and obtain the NAT64 prefix (such as <xref target="RFC7050"/>).
In that case the node SHOULD enable CLAT after discovering the NAT64 prefix, unless by that time the node has already obtained an IPv4 address.
</t>
<section anchor="ipv4detect">
<name>Detecting IPv4 Presence</name>
<t>
IPv6 interface configuration might completed faster than 
From performance perspective native IPv4 connectivity is preferrable over 464XLAT, so CLAT SHOULD NOT be enabled if the node has IPv4 connectivity over the given interface.
However the node SHOULD NOT wait for an explicit (DHCPv4 Option 108, <xref target="RFC8925"/>) or an implicit (DHCPv4 timeouts) indication that native IPv4 connectivity is not available.
Such delay would be impactful for IPv4-only applications, as such applications can not benefit from 464XLAT until CLAT is operational.
Therefore the node SHOULD enable CLAT as soon as possible and disable it later, if IPv4 connectivity becomes available.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="addr">
<name>
CLAT Addresses Considerations
</name>

<section anchor="v6addr">
<name>
CLAT IPv6 Addresses
</name>
<t>

</t>
</section>

<section anchor="v4addr">
<name>
CLAT IPv4 Addresses
</name>
</section>

</section>
<section anchor="disable">
<name>Disabling CLAT</name>
<t>
The node MAY chose to turn CLAT off if an IPv4 address becomes available after CLAT has started.
However turning it off would affect all applications and traffic flows already utilizing CLAT.
</t>
</section>
<section anchor="update">
<name>
Updates to RFC8585
</name>
<t>
This document makes the following changes to Section 3.2.1 of [RFC8585]:
</t>
<t>
OLD TEXT:
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>
464XLAT requirements:
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>
NEW TEXT:
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>
464XLAT requirements:
</t>
<t>
464XLAT-0:  The IPv6 Transition CE Router SHOULD follow recommendations provided in draft-link-v6ops-claton.
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>
OLD TEXT:
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>464XLAT-4: The IPv6 Transition CE Router MUST implement <xref target="RFC7050"/>
               ("Discovery of the IPv6 Prefix Used for IPv6 Address
               Synthesis") in order to discover the provider-side
               translator (PLAT) translation IPv4 and IPv6
               prefix(es)/suffix(es). </t>

<t>464XLAT-5: If PCP is implemented, the IPv6 Transition CE Router MUST
               follow <xref target="RFC7225"/> ("Discovering NAT64 IPv6 Prefixes Using
               the Port Control Protocol (PCP)") in order to learn the
               PLAT-side translation IPv4 and IPv6 prefix(es)/suffix(es)
               used by an upstream PCP-controlled NAT64 device. </t>

<t>464XLAT-6:  If the network provides several choices for the
               discovery/learning of the NAT64 prefix, the priority to
               use one or the other MUST follow this order: 1) <xref target="RFC7225"/>
               and 2) <xref target="RFC7050"/>.</t>
<t>
   The NAT64 prefix could be discovered by means of the method defined
   in <xref target="RFC7050"/> only if the service provider uses DNS64 [RFC6147].  It
   may be the case that the service provider does not use or does not
   trust DNS64 [RFC6147] because the DNS configuration at the CE (or
   hosts behind the CE) can be modified by the customer.  In that case,
   the service provider may opt to configure the NAT64 prefix by means
   of the option defined in <xref target="RFC7225"/>.  This can also be used if the
   service provider uses DNS64 [RFC6147].
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>
NEW TEXT
</t>
<t>
===
</t>
<t>464XLAT-4: The IPv6 Transition CE Router MUST implement <xref target="RFC8781"/> ("Discovering PREF64 in Router Advertisements") and <xref target="RFC7050"/>
               ("Discovery of the IPv6 Prefix Used for IPv6 Address
               Synthesis") in order to discover the provider-side
               translator (PLAT) translation IPv4 and IPv6
               prefix(es)/suffix(es). </t>

<t>464XLAT-5: If PCP is implemented, the IPv6 Transition CE Router MUST
               follow <xref target="RFC7225"/> ("Discovering NAT64 IPv6 Prefixes Using
               the Port Control Protocol (PCP)") in order to learn the
               PLAT-side translation IPv4 and IPv6 prefix(es)/suffix(es)
               used by an upstream PCP-controlled NAT64 device. </t>

<t>464XLAT-6:  If the network provides several choices for the
               discovery/learning of the NAT64 prefix, the priority to
               use one or the other MUST follow this order: 1) <xref target="RFC8781"/> 2)<xref target="RFC7225"/>
               and 3) <xref target="RFC7050"/>.</t>
<t>
   <xref target="RFC8781"/> allows the service provider to signal NAT64 prefix independntly from DNS64 presence.
   At the same time the NAT64 prefix could be discovered by means of the method defined
   in <xref target="RFC7050"/> only if the service provider uses DNS64 [RFC6147].  It
   may be the case that the service provider does not use or does not
   trust DNS64 [RFC6147] because the DNS configuration at the CE (or
   hosts behind the CE) can be modified by the customer.  In that case,
   the service provider may opt to configure the NAT64 prefix by means
   of the option defined in <xref target="RFC7225"/>.  This can also be used if the
   service provider uses DNS64 [RFC6147].
</t>
<t>
===
</t>

</section>
    <section anchor="Security">
      <!-- All drafts are required to have a security considerations section. See RFC 3552 for a guide. -->
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
<t>
If a malicious actor spoofs PLAT presence signals (such as an RA with PREF64 option) or DNS responses for DNS-based NAT64 prefix detection (<xref target="RFC7050"/>), traffic of IPv4-only applications using CLAT can be affected:
</t>
<ul>
<li>
<t>if there is no PLAT (NAT64) devices, traffic to NAT64 destinations would be dropped.</t>
</li>
<li>
<t>
If the attacker intercepts traffic for the NAT64 prefix (e.g. by providing the victim with a bogus NAT64 prefix and steering traffic for those destinations towards themselves), the attacker might be able to perform man-in-the-middle attack.
</t>
</li>
</ul>
<t>
Using PREF64 RA option to detect PLAT presence and the NAT64 prefix is less prone to such attacks, as the attacker needs to be on-link.
</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="privacy">
      <name>Privacy Considerations</name>
      <t>
This document does not introduce any privacy considerations.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="IANA">
    <!-- All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section. See RFC 8126 for a guide.-->
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This memo does not introduce any requests to IANA.</t>
    </section>
    
    <!-- NOTE: The Acknowledgements and Contributors sections are at the end of this template -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.6877.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7050.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8781.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8585.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.8925.xml"/>
        <!-- The recommended and simplest way to include a well known reference -->
        
      </references>
 
      <references>
	      <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.4862.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/refs/bibxml/reference.RFC.7225.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>
    
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
<t>
Thanks to Ondrej Caletka, Lorenzo Colitti, Ted Lemon, Jordi Palet, Dieter Siegmund for the discussions, the input and all contribution.
</t>
    </section>
    
 </back>
</rfc>
